Guide to the St. John's Lutheran Church of Potter records,1841-1921.
St. John's Lutheran Church of Potter records,1841-1921
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
St. John's Lutheran Church of Potter records, 1841-1921
6086
St. John's Lutheran Church of Potter (Potter, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
One volume register listing baptisms, confirmations, communicants, marriages, members and deaths and one volume of congregational meeting minutes which document the temporal affairs of the church.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Between 1828 and 1850 German Lutheran residents of Potter worshipped together in private homes or at the Boak Methodist Church in a group founded by Dr. Frederic Dutch, Jacob Shuman and Nicholas Heisler. In 1849 a meeting was held to plan building a church which was called Christ Church when completed in 1850. In 1856 the church changed its name to the Elsasser Congregation (a majority of its members being from Alsace) and in 1861 a committee was appointed to build a parsonage and a school room. In 1866 a new constitution was adopted and the church incorporated as the Evangelisch Lutherische Gemeinde. In 1919 the corporate name was changed to St. John's Evangelical Lutheran Church of Potter and Vicinity. A list of pastors and additional details are found in the accession folder.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Contains a one volume register listing baptisms, confirmations, communicants, marriages, members and deaths (1841-1888) and one volume of congregational meeting minutes (1849-1921) which deal with the temporal affairs of the church. Records are primarily in German until 1912 when a constitutional change allowed services in both languages. Thereafter most records are in English.
SUBJECTS
Names:
St. John's Lutheran Church of Potter (Potter, N.Y.); Christ Church (Potter, N.Y.); Elsasser Congregation (Potter, N.Y.); Evangelisch Lutherische Gemeinde (Potter, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Lutheran Church--New York (State)--Potter.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Potter.; Lutherans, German--New York (State)--Potter.
Places:
Yates County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Potter (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Baptismal certificates.; Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Church Record Book No. 1 1841-1846, Item 1
  Contains baptismal records (1841-1888), communion records (1844-1881), confirmations (1845-1887), marriages (1856-1888), deaths (1844, 51-87), and miscellaneous notes and comments. Occasional late entries are in English.
  - Baptisms
    Usually include names of parents, names of children, date of baptisms and birth, and names of witnesses, by pastor.
    - Page 3-34, January 1842 - 1861
    - Page 35-71, Date of birth not given. 1861-1879
    - Page 164-177, 1879-1885
    - Page 232-233, 1885 (single page tucked into volume)
    - Page 235-251, 1885-88 (mixed with other records)
    - Page 252, 1880
  - Confirmations
    Includes name and pastors.
    - Page 72-84, 1858-1881
    - Page 133-134, 1845-1853
    - Page 238, 1866 (for 7 people)
    - Page 244, 1887 (for 8 people)
    - Page 261, 1855, 1857
  - Communicants
    Communion usually held twice yearly.
    - Page 87-132, 1845-1867
    - Page 135-149, 1869-1881
    - Page 150-151, 1844
    - Page 152-163, 1882-1885
  - Marriages
    - Page 178-197, 1856-1885
    - Page 245, 1888
    - Page 259-260, 1846-1850
  - Deaths
    Name and date of death age in years, months and days.
    - Page 198-231, 1844-1887
    - Page 242, 1887 death notice
    - Page 253, 1888 - death of Georg Koehler with narrative concerning his poisining
    - Page 254-258, Members - list made 1882. Later, notes
    - Page 262-266, were made as to the disposition of the individual
  - Other
    - Page 268-271, n.d.
      Pages 39-42 from a printed book giving the rules of organization for churches in the Evangelical ministry of N.Y. state.
- Church Record Book No. 2 1849-1921, Item 2
  "The record of the Alsace congregation in the Town of Potter, County of Yates ..." Volume 2 contains minutes of congregational meetings (1849-1921) on the temporal affairs of the church. Minutes regularly include the results of trustee elections and financial reports. Most entries are in German until the 1880's, when they gradually switched to English. Items of note:
  - Page 3, December 1, 1849
    Members agree to build a church. Land offered for church and cemetary.
  - Page 4, October 21, 1850
    Record of the church's incorporation.
  - Page 6, October 1868
    Minutes out of order.
  - Page 11-21, April 25, 1857
    Articles of organization are included, including that only German shall be used in services, who can vote, trustees' responsibilities, officers, procedure to be followed in getting a new pastor, how one becomes a member, etc. Signed by 26 members.
  - Page 35, March 1869
    Mention of support for German immigrants to Buffalo and the Warlburg, Iowa seminary.
  - Page 52-68, 1885-1888
    Pastorate of Heinrich T. Duensing, who makes comments on the state of the church.
  - Page 77, July 29, 1894
    Constitutional changes made.
  - Page 77, January 2, 1918
    Women given the privilege of voting in church meeting
  - Page 77, 1918
    Funds raised for Wagner College.
  - Page 77, April 6, 1919
    Name anglicised.